About Us

This Research

This project is a part of Samantha Watkin's Bachelor of Philosophy thesis and THINK Fellowship research regarding empathy education in high school literature.

This Project

This project is an independent study relating to the crosslisted course ENGLIT 1600 Computational Methods in the Humanities.

Credits

Thank you to Professor David Birnbaum in the Slavics Department and Dr. Geoffrey Glover in the English Literature Department for mentoring me on this and every project.

Citations

Chapman, Alexander L. “Dialectical Behavior Therapy: Current Indications and Unique Elements.” Psychiatry (Edgmont (Pa. : Township)), Matrix Medical Communications, www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2963469/.

Dalzell, Jordan. “The Creation of a CBT Rating Scale for a Content Analysis of Children’s Storybooks.” Palo Alto University.

Mcculliss, Debbie, and David Chamberlain. “Bibliotherapy for Youth and Adolescents—School-Based Application and Research.” Journal of Poetry Therapy, vol. 26, no. 1, 2013, pp. 13–40., doi:10.1080/08893675.2013.764052.

Mehrabian, Albert, and Norman Epstein. “Emotional Empathy Questionnaire.” PsycTESTS Dataset, 1972, doi:10.1037/t06852-000.

Stallard, Paul, et al. “The Cognitive Behaviour Therapy Scale for Children and Young People (CBTS-CYP): Development and Psychometric Properties.” Behavioural and Cognitive Psychotherapy, vol. 42, no. 03, 2014, pp. 269–282., doi:10.1017/s135246581300115x.

“What Is Cognitive Behavioral Therapy?” American Psychological Association, American Psychological Association, www.apa.org/ptsd-guideline/patients-and-families/cognitive-behavioral.

Select a Text

Here is some content

story title here

discussion plan

Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Aliquam viverra lacus quis orci feugiat, a lobortis elit rutrum. In tempor, nisl vitae condimentum egestas, ex velit finibus nisl, et placerat est quam eget nulla. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia Curae; Sed rutrum non arcu vitae sollicitudin. Fusce molestie ex lorem, eu semper ligula semper vel. Maecenas sed dolor arcu. Praesent rutrum, magna ac posuere efficitur, lacus justo dignissim tellus, non condimentum erat purus vel lectus. Curabitur vel ipsum ornare, mollis nibh et, consequat lacus. Proin faucibus libero dolor, sed euismod urna tincidunt non. Quisque pulvinar risus vel risus dictum aliquet. Suspendisse euismod est eget enim venenatis tincidunt.

Nulla lectus ligula, faucibus at mauris non, finibus ullamcorper ipsum. Pellentesque venenatis id nisi et dignissim. Aenean ultrices ligula in ipsum placerat consequat. Fusce non facilisis risus. Morbi in turpis et enim dignissim mattis. Nunc id enim et sapien fermentum facilisis et ac diam. Praesent tristique, est a imperdiet vulputate, quam ipsum ullamcorper est, ut convallis velit mi quis sapien. Vestibulum id tortor neque. Suspendisse sit amet ultrices libero, in congue mauris. Donec fringilla congue felis, quis luctus metus accumsan eu. Curabitur convallis gravida est.

Fusce ac lectus luctus, porttitor ex in, fermentum est. Duis arcu diam, malesuada a est at, ornare facilisis diam. Nam consequat ultricies tortor, quis viverra lacus eleifend vel. Phasellus fringilla eget felis rutrum finibus. Integer eu augue rhoncus, ultricies erat pretium, interdum tellus. Nunc mattis, tellus ut rhoncus mattis, quam nisl commodo justo, nec facilisis ligula lorem eget nibh. Fusce vitae nulla sed nunc feugiat pharetra. Proin eu eros eu sem facilisis efficitur sed tincidunt massa. Curabitur euismod tellus quam. Sed ac venenatis ex. Duis ac mauris erat. Donec eleifend blandit nulla et ultrices. Sed ipsum dui, pharetra ac orci vel, pellentesque fermentum felis. Nunc risus magna, accumsan et ipsum ut, bibendum feugiat eros. Suspendisse sodales sit amet odio at commodo.

Praesent molestie quis tortor in pharetra. Maecenas a velit eu orci ultrices elementum. Cras non orci id nunc sodales cursus non vitae neque. Phasellus molestie leo eu nulla auctor commodo. Cras accumsan pulvinar hendrerit. Quisque pellentesque eget nisl non volutpat. Sed semper nibh eget metus condimentum, vitae imperdiet velit posuere. Vivamus sollicitudin tempor ultrices. Vestibulum gravida fringilla tincidunt. Aliquam erat volutpat.

Nunc congue turpis vitae purus lacinia, non accumsan velit placerat. Ut turpis elit, feugiat ullamcorper nunc ac, mollis efficitur est. Interdum et malesuada fames ac ante ipsum primis in faucibus. Nulla dignissim consectetur urna, vitae aliquam purus varius sed. Nunc in erat sed lorem euismod molestie et sed eros. Sed vel tristique ante, nec varius felis. Nam at velit tempus, aliquet nunc ut, blandit libero. Maecenas volutpat pulvinar diam, ac rhoncus leo rhoncus tempus. In dignissim dolor lobortis nisi feugiat, vel convallis dui gravida.

Maecenas at accumsan odio. Duis posuere fermentum urna sit amet commodo. Donec rhoncus felis at tortor ultrices, at egestas massa tempus. Phasellus a dignissim orci, quis imperdiet lacus. Cras sit amet lacus velit. Praesent venenatis laoreet tortor, ut blandit diam consectetur ut. Sed luctus dui augue, in commodo felis vehicula quis.

Vivamus ac egestas mauris, non commodo nisl. Pellentesque habitant morbi tristique senectus et netus et malesuada fames ac turpis egestas. Cras id convallis sem, quis volutpat orci. Fusce vestibulum ante et purus facilisis, ac mollis enim fermentum. Etiam pharetra aliquam lacus sed mollis. Aliquam est ipsum, tincidunt a aliquam eget, accumsan non nulla. Aenean pharetra diam sodales posuere condimentum. Maecenas ac molestie urna. Nam mi justo, suscipit ut vulputate eget, fringilla pulvinar libero. Vestibulum pulvinar ante quis sem aliquet porta. Nulla non egestas mi. Suspendisse pretium nec lacus id pellentesque. Praesent quis nulla imperdiet, consequat quam vel, tincidunt libero. Nullam ac nisl vitae est ullamcorper egestas. Suspendisse posuere risus sed diam suscipit pellentesque. Cras vel dui tincidunt, viverra tortor sed, convallis erat.

Vivamus accumsan felis nec ante vehicula, eu ultrices nisi auctor. Etiam diam urna, ullamcorper a est vitae, cursus vehicula diam. Curabitur quis massa quis ligula semper condimentum a ac velit. Fusce facilisis lorem mi, vel commodo ipsum varius nec. Sed vestibulum, ipsum id tincidunt posuere, augue arcu vestibulum odio, nec rutrum dui erat a metus. Integer dictum iaculis tellus, id pulvinar velit aliquam vel. Aliquam volutpat odio vel efficitur tempus. Curabitur nisl metus, mattis eget iaculis ut, pellentesque in mi. Nunc eget lorem in ante consectetur feugiat. Ut vulputate quam a erat congue, ac varius ante tempus. Nam ac purus facilisis, pharetra lorem vitae, cursus lectus. Curabitur tincidunt blandit lorem eget laoreet. Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Ut fringilla urna ac orci molestie commodo.

In ut varius leo. Vivamus imperdiet feugiat metus, eu pulvinar erat consectetur eu. Interdum et malesuada fames ac ante ipsum primis in faucibus. Vestibulum porttitor mattis purus, sit amet imperdiet ipsum condimentum sit amet. Nullam vel urna ac felis vehicula dictum. Sed tincidunt turpis in urna porttitor mattis. Vestibulum eleifend aliquam sodales. Aenean mollis orci sit amet iaculis consectetur. Integer pretium elit nisi, ac consequat nibh lobortis at. Etiam ut nulla lacinia, consequat lectus non, maximus velit. Mauris at odio vel nulla malesuada consectetur sed vitae nisi.

Vestibulum ut purus non ex fringilla tempus. Cras id tempor nulla. Nunc dignissim sem eget justo dictum, vitae fringilla tellus semper. Vestibulum tincidunt, lacus nec faucibus vehicula, quam nisl porta mauris, ut blandit nibh diam nec risus. Pellentesque convallis, sapien vitae ornare eleifend, quam odio fermentum odio, ut aliquet risus nisl efficitur mauris. Praesent sit amet scelerisque ipsum. Nulla commodo a felis quis viverra. Fusce sed elementum arcu, vitae sagittis elit. Proin nec pharetra mauris. Pellentesque congue scelerisque augue, vel vestibulum lacus scelerisque vel.

Pellentesque eleifend porttitor turpis, ac auctor tellus placerat in. Morbi rhoncus in ipsum eget lobortis. Curabitur viverra neque nec sem tincidunt, quis volutpat magna rutrum. Praesent id elit pretium, mollis enim vitae, cursus diam. Aliquam fermentum dictum rutrum. Quisque consequat justo ut finibus blandit. Ut varius tortor in nisi varius, at facilisis velit posuere. Sed malesuada consectetur vehicula. Pellentesque eget felis urna. Etiam aliquet, massa a euismod gravida, risus odio efficitur nisi, a tristique justo est nec purus. Praesent vel ligula nunc. Curabitur lacus tortor, dignissim at dolor quis, placerat pharetra lacus. Sed felis urna, porttitor vel erat et, suscipit egestas est.

The Comet

W.E.B. DuBois

Literaray Analysis

setting

sci-fi tropes

literary devices

themes

Critical Analysis

race

class

gender

orientation

ability

Opportunities for Empathy

CBT

DBT

Critical Thinking

Empathy

Text

Discussion Plan

He stood a moment on the steps of the bank, watching the human river that swirled down Broadway. Few noticed him. Few ever noticed him save in a way that stung. He was outside the world—"nothing!" as he said bitterly. Bits of the words of the walkers came to him.

"The comet?"

"The comet——"

Everybody was talking of it. Even the president, as he entered, smiled patronizingly at him, and asked:

"Well, Jim, are you scared?"

"No," said the messenger shortly.

"I thought we'd journeyed through the comet's tail once," broke in the junior clerk affably.

"Oh, that was Halley's," said the president; "this is a new comet, quite a stranger, they say—wonderful, wonderful! I saw it last night. Oh, by the way, Jim," turning again to the messenger, "I want you to go down into the lower vaults today."

The messenger followed the president silently. Of course, they wanted him to go down to the lower vaults. It was too dangerous for more valuable men. He smiled grimly and listened.

"Everything of value has been moved out since the water began to seep in," said the president; "but we miss two volumes of old records. Suppose you nose around down there,—it isn't very pleasant, I suppose."

"Not very," said the messenger, as he walked out.

"Well, Jim, the tail of the new comet hits us at noon this time," said the vault clerk, as he passed over the keys; but the messenger passed silently down the stairs. Down he went beneath Broadway, where the dim light filtered through the feet of hurrying men; down to the dark basement beneath; down into the blackness and silence beneath that lowest cavern. Here with his dark lantern he groped in the bowels of the earth, under the world.

He drew a long breath as he threw back the last great iron door and stepped into the fetid slime within. Here at last was peace, and he groped moodily forward. A great rat leaped past him and cobwebs crept across his face. He felt carefully around the room, shelf by shelf, on the muddied floor, and in crevice and corner. Nothing. Then he went back to the far end, where somehow the wall felt different. He sounded and pushed and pried. Nothing. He started away. Then something brought him back. He was sounding and working again when suddenly the whole black wall swung as on mighty hinges, and blackness yawned beyond. He peered in; it was evidently a secret vault—some hiding place of the old bank unknown in newer times. He entered hesitatingly. It was a long, narrow room with shelves, and at the far end, an old iron chest. On a high shelf lay the two missing volumes of records, and others. He put them carefully aside and stepped to the chest. It was old, strong, and rusty. He looked at the vast and old-fashioned lock and flashed his light on the hinges. They were deeply incrusted with rust. Looking about, he found a bit of iron and began to pry. The rust had eaten a hundred years, and it had gone deep. Slowly, wearily, the old lid lifted, and with a last, low groan lay bare its treasure—and he saw the dull sheen of gold!

"Boom!"

A low, grinding, reverberating crash struck upon his ear. He started up and looked about. All was black and still. He groped for his light and swung it about him. Then he knew! The great stone door had swung to. He forgot the gold and looked death squarely in the face. Then with a sigh he went methodically to work. The cold sweat stood on his forehead; but he searched, pounded, pushed, and worked until after what seemed endless hours his hand struck a cold bit of metal and the great door swung again harshly on its hinges, and then, striking against something soft and heavy, stopped. He had just room to squeeze through. There lay the body of the vault clerk, cold and stiff. He stared at it, and then felt sick and nauseated. The air seemed unaccountably foul, with a strong, peculiar odor. He stepped forward, clutched at the air, and fell fainting across the corpse.

He awoke with a sense of horror, leaped from the body, and groped up the stairs, calling to the guard. The watchman sat as if asleep, with the gate swinging free. With one glance at him the messenger hurried up to the sub-vault. In vain he called to the guards. His voice echoed and re-echoed weirdly. Up into the great basement he rushed. Here another guard lay prostrate on his face, cold and still. A fear arose in the messenger's heart. He dashed up to the cellar floor, up into the bank. The stillness of death lay everywhere and everywhere bowed, bent, and stretched the silent forms of men. The messenger paused and glanced about. He was not a man easily moved; but the sight was appalling! "Robbery and murder," he whispered slowly to himself as he saw the twisted, oozing mouth of the president where he lay half-buried on his desk. Then a new thought seized him: If they found him here alone—with all this money and all these dead men—what would his life be worth? He glanced about, tiptoed cautiously to a side door, and again looked behind. Quietly he turned the latch and stepped out into Wall Street.

How silent the street was! Not a soul was stirring, and yet it was high-noon—Wall Street? Broadway? He glanced almost wildly up and down, then across the street, and as he looked, a sickening horror froze in his limbs. With a choking cry of utter fright he lunged, leaned giddily against the cold building, and stared helplessly at the sight.

In the great stone doorway a hundred men and women and children lay crushed and twisted and jammed, forced into that great, gaping doorway like refuse in a can—as if in one wild, frantic rush to safety, they had rushed and ground themselves to death. Slowly the messenger crept along the walls, wetting his parched mouth and trying to comprehend, stilling the tremor in his limbs and the rising terror in his heart. He met a business man, silk-hatted and frock-coated, who had crept, too, along that smooth wall and stood now stone dead with wonder written on his lips. The messenger turned his eyes hastily away and sought the curb. A woman leaned wearily against the signpost, her head bowed motionless on her lace and silken bosom. Before her stood a street car, silent, and within—but the messenger but glanced and hurried on. A grimy newsboy sat in the gutter with the "last edition" in his uplifted hand: "Danger!" screamed its black headlines. "Warnings wired around the world. The Comet's tail sweeps past us at noon. Deadly gases expected. Close doors and windows. Seek the cellar." The messenger read and staggered on. Far out from a window above, a girl lay with gasping face and sleevelets on her arms. On a store step sat a little, sweet-faced girl looking upward toward the skies, and in the carriage by her lay—but the messenger looked no longer. The cords gave way—the terror burst in his veins, and with one great, gasping cry he sprang desperately forward and ran,—ran as only the frightened run, shrieking and fighting the air until with one last wail of pain he sank on the grass of Madison Square and lay prone and still.

When he rose, he gave no glance at the still and silent forms on the benches, but, going to a fountain, bathed his face; then hiding himself in a corner away from the drama of death, he quietly gripped himself and thought the thing through: The comet had swept the earth and this was the end. Was everybody dead? He must search and see.

He knew that he must steady himself and keep calm, or he would go insane. First he must go to a restaurant. He walked up Fifth Avenue to a famous hostelry and entered its gorgeous, ghost-haunted halls. He beat back the nausea, and, seizing a tray from dead hands, hurried into the street and ate ravenously, hiding to keep out the sights.

"Yesterday, they would not have served me," he whispered, as he forced the food down.

Then he started up the street,—looking, peering, telephoning, ringing alarms; silent, silent all. Was nobody—nobody—he dared not think the thought and hurried on.

Suddenly he stopped still. He had forgotten. My God! How could he have forgotten? He must rush to the subway—then he almost laughed. No—a car; if he could find a Ford. He saw one. Gently he lifted off its burden, and took his place on the seat. He tested the throttle. There was gas. He glided off, shivering, and drove up the street. Everywhere stood, leaned, lounged, and lay the dead, in grim and awful silence. On he ran past an automobile, wrecked and overturned; past another, filled with a gay party whose smiles yet lingered on their death-struck lips; on past crowds and groups of cars, pausing by dead policemen; at 42nd Street he had to detour to Park Avenue to avoid the dead congestion. He came back on Fifth Avenue at 57th and flew past the Plaza and by the park with its hushed babies and silent throng, until as he was rushing past 72nd Street he heard a sharp cry, and saw a living form leaning wildly out an upper window. He gasped. The human voice sounded in his ears like the voice of God.

"Hello—hello—help, in God's name!" wailed the woman. "There's a dead girl in here and a man and—and see yonder dead men lying in the street and dead horses—for the love of God go and bring the officers——" And the words trailed off into hysterical tears.

He wheeled the car in a sudden circle, running over the still body of a child and leaping on the curb. Then he rushed up the steps and tried the door and rang violently. There was a long pause, but at last the heavy door swung back. They stared a moment in silence. She had not noticed before that he was a Negro. He had not thought of her as white. She was a woman of perhaps twenty-five—rarely beautiful and richly gowned, with darkly-golden hair, and jewels. Yesterday, he thought with bitterness, she would scarcely have looked at him twice. He would have been dirt beneath her silken feet. She stared at him. Of all the sorts of men she had pictured as coming to her rescue she had not dreamed of one like him. Not that he was not human, but he dwelt in a world so far from hers, so infinitely far, that he seldom even entered her thought. Yet as she looked at him curiously he seemed quite commonplace and usual. He was a tall, dark workingman of the better class, with a sensitive face trained to stolidity and a poor man's clothes and hands. His face was soft and slow and his manner at once cold and nervous, like fires long banked, but not out.

So a moment each paused and gauged the other; then the thought of the dead world without rushed in and they started toward each other.

"What has happened?" she cried. "Tell me! Nothing stirs. All is silence! I see the dead strewn before my window as winnowed by the breath of God,—and see——" She dragged him through great, silken hangings to where, beneath the sheen of mahogany and silver, a little French maid lay stretched in quiet, everlasting sleep, and near her a butler lay prone in his livery.

The tears streamed down the woman's cheeks and she clung to his arm until the perfume of her breath swept his face and he felt the tremors racing through her body.

"I had been shut up in my dark room developing pictures of the comet which I took last night; when I came out—I saw the dead!

"What has happened?" she cried again.

He answered slowly:

"Something—comet or devil—swept across the earth this morning and—many are dead!"

"Many? Very many?"

"I have searched and I have seen no other living soul but you."

She gasped and they stared at each other.

"My—father!" she whispered.

"Where is he?"

"He started for the office."

"Where is it?"

"In the Metropolitan Tower."

"Leave a note for him here and come."

Then he stopped.

"No," he said firmly—"first, we must go—to Harlem."

"Harlem!" she cried. Then she understood. She tapped her foot at first impatiently. She looked back and shuddered. Then she came resolutely down the steps.

"There's a swifter car in the garage in the court," she said.

"I don't know how to drive it," he said.

"I do," she answered.

In ten minutes they were flying to Harlem on the wind. The Stutz rose and raced like an airplane. They took the turn at 110th Street on two wheels and slipped with a shriek into 135th.

He was gone but a moment. Then he returned, and his face was gray. She did not look, but said:

"You have lost—somebody?"

"I have lost—everybody," he said, simply—"unless——"

He ran back and was gone several minutes—hours they seemed to her.

"Everybody," he said, and he walked slowly back with something film-like in his hand which he stuffed into his pocket.

"I'm afraid I was selfish," he said. But already the car was moving toward the park among the dark and lined dead of Harlem—the brown, still faces, the knotted hands, the homely garments, and the silence—the wild and haunting silence. Out of the park, and down Fifth Avenue they whirled. In and out among the dead they slipped and quivered, needing no sound of bell or horn, until the great, square Metropolitan Tower hove in sight. Gently he laid the dead elevator boy aside; the car shot upward. The door of the office stood open. On the threshold lay the stenographer, and, staring at her, sat the dead clerk. The inner office was empty, but a note lay on the desk, folded and addressed but unsent:

Dear Daughter:

I've gone for a hundred mile spin in Fred's new Mercedes. Shall not be back before dinner. I'll bring Fred with me.

J.B.H.

"Come," she cried nervously. "We must search the city."

Up and down, over and across, back again—on went that ghostly search. Everywhere was silence and death—death and silence! They hunted from Madison Square to Spuyten Duyvel; they rushed across the Williamsburg Bridge; they swept over Brooklyn; from the Battery and Morningside Heights they scanned the river. Silence, silence everywhere, and no human sign. Haggard and bedraggled they puffed a third time slowly down Broadway, under the broiling sun, and at last stopped. He sniffed the air. An odor—a smell—and with the shifting breeze a sickening stench filled their nostrils and brought its awful warning. The girl settled back helplessly in her seat.

"What can we do?" she cried.

It was his turn now to take the lead, and he did it quickly.

"The long distance telephone—the telegraph and the cable—night rockets and then—flight!"

She looked at him now with strength and confidence. He did not look like men, as she had always pictured men; but he acted like one and she was content. In fifteen minutes they were at the central telephone exchange. As they came to the door he stepped quickly before her and pressed her gently back as he closed it. She heard him moving to and fro, and knew his burdens—the poor, little burdens he bore. When she entered, he was alone in the room. The grim switchboard flashed its metallic face in cryptic, sphinx-like immobility. She seated herself on a stool and donned the bright earpiece. She looked at the mouthpiece. She had never looked at one so closely before. It was wide and black, pimpled with usage; inert; dead; almost sarcastic in its unfeeling curves. It looked—she beat back the thought—but it looked,—it persisted in looking like—she turned her head and found herself alone. One moment she was terrified; then she thanked him silently for his delicacy and turned resolutely, with a quick intaking of breath.

"Hello!" she called in low tones. She was calling to the world. The world must answer. Would the world answer? Was the world——

Silence!

She had spoken too low.

"Hello!" she cried, full-voiced.

She listened. Silence! Her heart beat quickly. She cried in clear, distinct, loud tones: "Hello—hello—hello!"

What was that whirring? Surely—no—was it the click of a receiver?

She bent close, she moved the pegs in the holes, and called and called, until her voice rose almost to a shriek, and her heart hammered. It was as if she had heard the last flicker of creation, and the evil was silence. Her voice dropped to a sob. She sat stupidly staring into the black and sarcastic mouthpiece, and the thought came again. Hope lay dead within her. Yes, the cable and the rockets remained; but the world—she could not frame the thought or say the word. It was too mighty—too terrible! She turned toward the door with a new fear in her heart. For the first time she seemed to realize that she was alone in the world with a stranger, with something more than a stranger,—with a man alien in blood and culture—unknown, perhaps unknowable. It was awful! She must escape—she must fly; he must not see her again. Who knew what awful thoughts—

She gathered her silken skirts deftly about her young, smooth limbs—listened, and glided into a sidehall. A moment she shrank back: the hall lay filled with dead women; then she leaped to the door and tore at it, with bleeding fingers, until it swung wide. She looked out. He was standing at the top of the alley,—silhouetted, tall and black, motionless. Was he looking at her or away? She did not know—she did not care. She simply leaped and ran—ran until she found herself alone amid the dead and the tall ramparts of towering buildings.

She stopped. She was alone. Alone! Alone on the streets—alone in the city—perhaps alone in the world! There crept in upon her the sense of deception—of creeping hands behind her back—of silent, moving things she could not see,—of voices hushed in fearsome conspiracy. She looked behind and sideways, started at strange sounds and heard still stranger, until every nerve within her stood sharp and quivering, stretched to scream at the barest touch. She whirled and flew back, whimpering like a child, until she found that narrow alley again and the dark, silent figure silhouetted at the top. She stopped and rested; then she walked silently toward him, looked at him timidly; but he said nothing as he handed her into the car. Her voice caught as she whispered:

"Not—that."

And he answered slowly: "No—not that!"

They climbed into the car. She bent forward on the wheel and sobbed, with great, dry, quivering sobs, as they flew toward the cable office on the east side, leaving the world of wealth and prosperity for the world of poverty and work. In the world behind them were death and silence, grave and grim, almost cynical, but always decent; here it was hideous. It clothed itself in every ghastly form of terror, struggle, hate, and suffering. It lay wreathed in crime and squalor, greed and lust. Only in its dread and awful silence was it like to death everywhere.

Yet as the two, flying and alone, looked upon the horror of the world, slowly, gradually, the sense of all-enveloping death deserted them. They seemed to move in a world silent and asleep,—not dead. They moved in quiet reverence, lest somehow they wake these sleeping forms who had, at last, found peace. They moved in some solemn, world-wide Friedhof, above which some mighty arm had waved its magic wand. All nature slept until—until, and quick with the same startling thought, they looked into each other's eyes—he, ashen, and she, crimson, with unspoken thought. To both, the vision of a mighty beauty—of vast, unspoken things, swelled in their souls; but they put it away.

Great, dark coils of wire came up from the earth and down from the sun and entered this low lair of witchery. The gathered lightnings of the world centered here, binding with beams of light the ends of the earth. The doors gaped on the gloom within. He paused on the threshold.

"Do you know the code?" she asked.

"I know the call for help—we used it formerly at the bank."

She hardly heard. She heard the lapping of the waters far below,—the dark and restless waters—the cold and luring waters, as they called. He stepped within. Slowly she walked to the wall, where the water called below, and stood and waited. Long she waited, and he did not come. Then with a start she saw him, too, standing beside the black waters. Slowly he removed his coat and stood there silently. She walked quickly to him and laid her hand on his arm. He did not start or look. The waters lapped on in luring, deadly rhythm. He pointed down to the waters, and said quietly:

"The world lies beneath the waters now—may I go?"

She looked into his stricken, tired face, and a great pity surged within her heart. She answered in a voice clear and calm, "No."

Upward they turned toward life again, and he seized the wheel. The world was darkening to twilight, and a great, gray pall was falling mercifully and gently on the sleeping dead. The ghastly glare of reality seemed replaced with the dream of some vast romance. The girl lay silently back, as the motor whizzed along, and looked half-consciously for the elf-queen to wave life into this dead world again. She forgot to wonder at the quickness with which he had learned to drive her car. It seemed natural. And then as they whirled and swung into Madison Square and at the door of the Metropolitan Tower she gave a low cry, and her eyes were great! Perhaps she had seen the elf-queen?

The man led her to the elevator of the tower and deftly they ascended. In her father's office they gathered rugs and chairs, and he wrote a note and laid it on the desk; then they ascended to the roof and he made her comfortable. For a while she rested and sank to dreamy somnolence, watching the worlds above and wondering. Below lay the dark shadows of the city and afar was the shining of the sea. She glanced at him timidly as he set food before her and took a shawl and wound her in it, touching her reverently, yet tenderly. She looked up at him with thankfulness in her eyes, eating what he served. He watched the city. She watched him. He seemed very human,—very near now.

"Have you had to work hard?" she asked softly.

"Always," he said.

"I have always been idle," she said. "I was rich."

"I was poor," he almost echoed.

"The rich and the poor are met together," she began, and he finished:

"The Lord is the Maker of them all."

"Yes," she said slowly; "and how foolish our human distinctions seem—now," looking down to the great dead city stretched below, swimming in unlightened shadows.

"Yes—I was not—human, yesterday," he said.

She looked at him. "And your people were not my people," she said; "but today——" She paused. He was a man,—no more; but he was in some larger sense a gentleman,—sensitive, kindly, chivalrous, everything save his hands and—his face. Yet yesterday——

"Death, the leveler!" he muttered.

"And the revealer," she whispered gently, rising to her feet with great eyes. He turned away, and after fumbling a moment sent a rocket into the darkening air. It arose, shrieked, and flew up, a slim path of light, and scattering its stars abroad, dropped on the city below. She scarcely noticed it. A vision of the world had risen before her. Slowly the mighty prophecy of her destiny overwhelmed her. Above the dead past hovered the Angel of Annunciation. She was no mere woman. She was neither high nor low, white nor black, rich nor poor. She was primal woman; mighty mother of all men to come and Bride of Life. She looked upon the man beside her and forgot all else but his manhood, his strong, vigorous manhood—his sorrow and sacrifice. She saw him glorified. He was no longer a thing apart, a creature below, a strange outcast of another clime and blood, but her Brother Humanity incarnate, Son of God and great All-Father of the race to be.

He did not glimpse the glory in her eyes, but stood looking outward toward the sea and sending rocket after rocket into the unanswering darkness. Dark-purple clouds lay banked and billowed in the west. Behind them and all around, the heavens glowed in dim, weird radiance that suffused the darkening world and made almost a minor music. Suddenly, as though gathered back in some vast hand, the great cloud-curtain fell away. Low on the horizon lay a long, white star—mystic, wonderful! And from it fled upward to the pole, like some wan bridal veil, a pale, wide sheet of flame that lighted all the world and dimmed the stars.

In fascinated silence the man gazed at the heavens and dropped his rockets to the floor. Memories of memories stirred to life in the dead recesses of his mind. The shackles seemed to rattle and fall from his soul. Up from the crass and crushing and cringing of his caste leaped the lone majesty of kings long dead. He arose within the shadows, tall, straight, and stern, with power in his eyes and ghostly scepters hovering to his grasp. It was as though some mighty Pharaoh lived again, or curled Assyrian lord. He turned and looked upon the lady, and found her gazing straight at him.

Silently, immovably, they saw each other face to face—eye to eye. Their souls lay naked to the night. It was not lust; it was not love—it was some vaster, mightier thing that needed neither touch of body nor thrill of soul. It was a thought divine, splendid.

Slowly, noiselessly, they moved toward each other—the heavens above, the seas around, the city grim and dead below. He loomed from out the velvet shadows vast and dark. Pearl-white and slender, she shone beneath the stars. She stretched her jeweled hands abroad. He lifted up his mighty arms, and they cried each to the other, almost with one voice, "The world is dead."

"Long live the——"

"Honk! Honk!" Hoarse and sharp the cry of a motor drifted clearly up from the silence below. They started backward with a cry and gazed upon each other with eyes that faltered and fell, with blood that boiled.

"Honk! Honk! Honk! Honk!" came the mad cry again, and almost from their feet a rocket blazed into the air and scattered its stars upon them. She covered her eyes with her hands, and her shoulders heaved. He dropped and bowed, groped blindly on his knees about the floor. A blue flame spluttered lazily after an age, and she heard the scream of an answering rocket as it flew.

Then they stood still as death, looking to opposite ends of the earth.

"Clang—crash—clang!"

The roar and ring of swift elevators shooting upward from below made the great tower tremble. A murmur and babel of voices swept in upon the night. All over the once dead city the lights blinked, flickered, and flamed; and then with a sudden clanging of doors the entrance to the platform was filled with men, and one with white and flying hair rushed to the girl and lifted her to his breast. "My daughter!" he sobbed.

Behind him hurried a younger, comelier man, carefully clad in motor costume, who bent above the girl with passionate solicitude and gazed into her staring eyes until they narrowed and dropped and her face flushed deeper and deeper crimson.

"Julia," he whispered; "my darling, I thought you were gone forever."

She looked up at him with strange, searching eyes.

"Fred," she murmured, almost vaguely, "is the world—gone?"

"Only New York," he answered; "it is terrible—awful! You know,—but you, how did you escape—how have you endured this horror? Are you well? Unharmed?"

"Unharmed!" she said.

"And this man here?" he asked, encircling her drooping form with one arm and turning toward the Negro. Suddenly he stiffened and his hand flew to his hip. "Why!" he snarled. "It's—a—nigger—Julia! Has he—has he dared——"

She lifted her head and looked at her late companion curiously and then dropped her eyes with a sigh.

"He has dared—all, to rescue me," she said quietly, "and I—thank him—much." But she did not look at him again. As the couple turned away, the father drew a roll of bills from his pockets.

"Here, my good fellow," he said, thrusting the money into the man's hands, "take that,—what's your name?"

"Jim Davis," came the answer, hollow-voiced.

"Well, Jim, I thank you. I've always liked your people. If you ever want a job, call on me." And they were gone.

The crowd poured up and out of the elevators, talking and whispering.

"Who was it?"

"Are they alive?"

"How many?"

"Two!"

"Who was saved?"

"A white girl and a nigger—there she goes."

"A nigger? Where is he? Let's lynch the damned——"

"Shut up—he's all right-he saved her."

"Saved hell! He had no business——"

"Here he comes."

Into the glare of the electric lights the colored man moved slowly, with the eyes of those that walk and sleep.

"Well, what do you think of that?" cried a bystander; "of all New York, just a white girl and a nigger!"

The colored man heard nothing. He stood silently beneath the glare of the light, gazing at the money in his hand and shrinking as he gazed; slowly he put his other hand into his pocket and brought out a baby's filmy cap, and gazed again. A woman mounted to the platform and looked about, shading her eyes. She was brown, small, and toil-worn, and in one arm lay the corpse of a dark baby. The crowd parted and her eyes fell on the colored man; with a cry she tottered toward him.

"Jim!"

He whirled and, with a sob of joy, caught her in his arms.

Organized by Topic

CBT

What is Julia thinking in this moment? What does she realize? What does her subsequent behavior reflect on her?
In your opinion, was Jim selfish?
Put yourself in Julia's shoes. What are her options in this scene? Which option would you choose and why?
Why do Julia and Jim's mentalities shift from viewing the world as dead to viewing the world as sleeping?
Julia first felt called by the waters, but it was Jim who asked to go. How does this contribute to their character development?
Previously, Julia had thought her hope had died, regardless of the rockets. Now she has new hope. What inspired it?
What traits humanize Jim? What is said to alienate him?

DBT

Put yourself in Jim's shoes. If you were in this situation what would you think? What would you do?
Consider the choise of language in these three lines. What does it mean that Julia answered a question that was not asked? What assumptions does Jim make?
There is religious imagery throughout the story; here the characters quote Proverbs 22:2. Is religion a force of equality in this story? If so, how? If not, what is it's function?
What is the distinction between a man and a gentleman? Which traits do the other male characters in the story embody?

Empathy

Imagine Jim's world that this is where he finds peace. Compare and contrast it to your own.
She had a very real concern, one that women experience daily, that Jim hadn't even considered. What concerns are unique to each character and how has the end of society changed those concerns?

Critical Thinking

Why is there a secret vault and what does the passage of time signify? Why is it meaningful that he found a vault?
What would have happened if the stone door hadn't sealed Jim into the anex?
With the information you have so far, make an educated guess as to what happened while Jim was in the cellar.
Discuss the irony in this scene. What do you take away from it? What did the author intend for the reader to understand about society based on this scene?
Compare and contrast the spaces that protected Jim and Julia from the comet respectively. What do they say about the characters?
What do you think Jim went back to check? What do you think he brought back?
What is the importance of place in this text?
Consider the language applied to Julia: how she often cries out or behaves helplessly. What is DuBois trying to say about her character?
How does technology provide hope in this story? With the antagonist being a force of nature, does this story conform or subvert genre standards in it's use of technology
What is this paragraph trying to say? What is the author trying to say? Compare and contrast how death is portrayed in relation to wealth throughout the text.
Why is the cable office viewed as a low lair of witchery?
What does it say about Jim that he is able to make this allusion to a poem from 1659? What is DuBois trying to tell the reader?
Why does Julia's name first appear so late in the story?
What does the symbol of the baby represent?
Society is reintroduced. Julia's community returns. What is the function of having Jim's community also return?

In Story Order

Imagine Jim's world that this is where he finds peace. Compare and contrast it to your own.

"Here at last was peace"

Why is there a secret vault and what does the passage of time signify? Why is it meaningful that he found a vault?

"it was evidently a secret vault—some hiding place of the old bank unknown in newer times."

What does the chest represent? What would you do in Jim's situation if you found a chest of gold?

"It was old, strong, and rusty."

What would have happened if the stone door hadn't sealed Jim into the anex?

"The great stone door had swung to."

Put yourself in Jim's shoes. If you were in this situation what would you think? What would you do?

"If they found him here alone—with all this money and all these dead men—what would his life be worth?"

With the information you have so far, make an educated guess as to what happened while Jim was in the cellar.

"He met a business man, silk—hatted and frock—coated, who had crept, too, along that smooth wall and stood now stone dead with wonder written on his lips."

Discuss the irony in this scene. What do you take away from it? What did the author intend for the reader to understand about society based on this scene?

"The messenger read and staggered on."

Compare and contrast the spaces that protected Jim and Julia from the comet respectively. What do they say about the characters?

"I had been shut up in my dark room developing pictures of the comet which I took last night; when I came out—I saw the dead!"

What is Julia thinking in this moment? What does she realize? What does her subsequent behavior reflect on her?

"Then she understood."

Consider the choise of language in these three lines. What does it mean that Julia answered a question that was not asked? What assumptions does Jim make?

"she answered."

What do you think Jim went back to check? What do you think he brought back?

"he walked slowly back with something film—like in his hand which he stuffed into his pocket."

In your opinion, was Jim selfish?

"I'm afraid I was selfish, he said."

What is the importance of place in this text?

"Up and down, over and across, back again—on went that ghostly search. Everywhere was silence and death—death and silence! They hunted from Madison Square to Spuyten Duyvel; they rushed across the Williamsburg Bridge; they swept over Brooklyn; from the Battery and Morningside Heights they scanned the river. Silence, silence everywhere, and no human sign. Haggard and bedraggled they puffed a third time slowly down Broadway, under the broiling sun, and at last stopped."

Consider the language applied to Julia: how she often cries out or behaves helplessly. What is DuBois trying to say about her character?

"The girl settled back helplessly in her seat."

How does technology provide hope in this story? With the antagonist being a force of nature, does this story conform or subvert genre standards in it's use of technology

"Hope lay dead within her. Yes, the cable and the rockets remained; but the world"

What is the power of the male gaze and male presence in this scene?

"Was he looking at her or away?"

Put yourself in Julia's shoes. What are her options in this scene? Which option would you choose and why?

"She looked behind and sideways, started at strange sounds and heard still stranger, until every nerve within her stood sharp and quivering, stretched to scream at the barest touch."

She had a very real concern, one that women experience daily, that Jim hadn't even considered. What concerns are unique to each character and how has the end of society changed those concerns?

"And he answered slowly: No—not that!"

What is this paragraph trying to say? What is the author trying to say? Compare and contrast how death is portrayed in relation to wealth throughout the text.

"the world of wealth and prosperity for the world of poverty and work. In the world behind them were death and silence, grave and grim, almost cynical, but always decent; here it was hideous. It clothed itself in every ghastly form of terror, struggle, hate, and suffering. It lay wreathed in crime and squalor, greed and lust. Only in its dread and awful silence was it like to death everywhere."

Why do Julia and Jim's mentalities shift from viewing the world as dead to viewing the world as sleeping?

"Yet as the two, flying and alone, looked upon the horror of the world, slowly, gradually, the sense of all—enveloping death deserted them. They seemed to move in a world silent and asleep,—not dead. They moved in quiet reverence, lest somehow they wake these sleeping forms who had, at last, found peace."

Why is the cable office viewed as a low lair of witchery?

"low lair of witchery"

Julia first felt called by the waters, but it was Jim who asked to go. How does this contribute to their character development?

"She walked quickly to him and laid her hand on his arm. He did not start or look."

There is religious imagery throughout the story; here the characters quote Proverbs 22:2. Is religion a force of equality in this story? If so, how? If not, what is it's function?

"The Lord is the Maker of them all."

What is the distinction between a man and a gentleman? Which traits do the other male characters in the story embody?

"He was a man,—no more; but he was in some larger sense a gentleman,—sensitive, kindly, chivalrous, everything save his hands and—his face."

What does it say about Jim that he is able to make this allusion to a poem from 1659? What is DuBois trying to tell the reader?

"Death, the leveler!"

Previously, Julia had thought her hope had died, regardless of the rockets. Now she has new hope. What inspired it?

"She scarcely noticed it."

Why does Julia's name first appear so late in the story?

"Julia"

What traits humanize Jim? What is said to alienate him?

"The colored man heard nothing."

What does the symbol of the baby represent?

"She was brown, small, and toil—worn, and in one arm lay the corpse of a dark baby."

Society is reintroduced. Julia's community returns. What is the function of having Jim's community also return?

"He whirled and, with a sob of joy, caught her in his arms."

Read More About Discussion Plans Here

Methodology:

An Application of Empathy Development Methodology for Use by Teachers

Key Principles

This project proffers that empathy can be developed in literature classrooms through the use of cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) and dialectical-behavioral therapy (DBT) in bibliotherapy.

What is Bibliotherapy and Why Use It?

Bibliotherapy is “the process of using books to help youth and adolescents think about, understand, and work through social and emotional issues.” (Miller, 2009) That is to say, there is great power in a good book. By discussing literature students can actually undergo social and emotional development.

Bibliotherapy has three primary goals: (1) to illustrate characters and problems so that readers recognize that their lived experience is shared by others in order to make them feel less isolated. For example a student with a disability who has never met another person with a similar disability may feel isolated but by reading texts that feature a character that they identify with, they may feel less isolated in their experience. (2) To evoke changes in values and attitudes such as empathy and tolerance. This can be done by introducing students to perspectives that differ from their own; a rural white student who has never met a person of color may struggle to empathize with the experience of victims of racial violence, but by conducting bibliotherapy using texts with characters of color, the student may better be able to recognize their shared humanity and better identify with individuals dissimilar to themself. And (3) to induce cognitive changes such as increased critical thinking, problem solving, and resourcefulness. This can be done by asking students comprehension questions and challenging them to interact deeply with the text, perhaps coming up with solutions to problems or inserting themselves into situations as they read.

This process can be done through large or small group discussion but can also be done through self-guided reading, writing exercises, or art projects.

Bibliotherapy is a different way of looking at class discussions that can be integrated simply with small steps such as including questions that invite the reader’s perspective and invite students to challenge and be challenged by the story.

What is CBT and DBT?

Cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) is a therapeutic treatment that challenges unhelpful ways of thinking and behaving to help improve a practitioner’s mood. In the simplest terms, sometimes we think things or do things that hurt us, but CBT can help us learn new ways of thinking and behaving to circumnavigate these bad habits. In this project, the main take away from CBT is the idea of “cognitive distortions” or ways of thinking about situations that are stilted by interpretation and not based on fact. Bibliotherapy techniques will be used to help students challenge the cognitive distortions they observe in the text to help them extrapolate to their own ways of thinking. For a complete list of cognitive distortions as defined in this project, please visit this link to The Pennsylvania Child Welfare Resource Center.

Dialectical-behavioral therapy (DBT) is more focused on interpersonal relationships. The main take away from DBT is the development of a consistent dialectical philosophy, that is to say, developing the idea that there are multiple points of view on every issue and topic and that there is no absolute truth which is particularly relevant to both literature and empathy. Students who are able to recognize that there are multiple points of view will be better capable of recognizing the points of view of others.

Selecting Texts

The most important thing when it comes to selecting a text to use for this process is that the students are comfortable with it. Beyond that, there are different nuances in the criteria depending on the specific group goal, but overall the text needs to be: on the students’ reading level, be engaging and clear, and demonstrate diversity. Often texts are chosen that demonstrate coping skills but because the focus of this project is on in classroom application, we are focusing on texts that are more general. For your classroom, try to choose texts that feature diverse characters and perspectives and do not lock students into a single point of view.

Proceed to Step 2

Implementation

An Application of Empathy Development Methodology for Use by Teachers

Theory

Practical Strategies

Prater, Johnstun, Dyches, and Johnstun, in their work Using Children's Books as Bibliotherapy for At-Risk Students: A Guide for Teachers lay out a ten-step program for developmental bibliotherapy. The steps are as follows:

Develop rapport, trust, and confidence with the student
Identify other school personnel who may assist
Solicit support from the student’s parents or guardians
Define a specific problem the student is experiencing
Create goals and activities to address the problem
Research and select books appropriate for the situation
Introduce the book to the student
Incorporate reading activities,
Implement postreading activities
Evaluate the effects of bibliotherapy on the student

This resource aims to assist with steps 4-10.

The specific problem in this case is developing empathy, though this can be done in conjunction with other goals. It is important to set explicit goals to avoid causing harm to students by leaving things unresolved. (Prater, 2006, 7)

Selecting texts can be done in tandem with your school's librarian or counselor if specific issues are needing to be addressed. However, as many teachers are required to choose from a predetermined list of texts, on the next page we explain how to orient canonical texts for bibliotherapeutic purposes.

Introducing the book to students is an important step because it allows students to have a stake in the activity. Give students a voice in the work they do, what they read, and they will engage more fully. (Morrison, 53)

The next page provides more concrete information regarding reading and post reading activities, but the general idea is that reading alone will not engage students in the discourse that needs to be had. Different activities and discussion models can be applied to keep students interested and learning.

To evaluate the effectiveness of the intervention, you may simply reflect on the work students conducted and observe how you could change your proceedured to better meet the students' needs and to engage them more fully. You may also implement the use of pre and post tests and observational assessment metrics if you want your evaluation to be more complete. Regardless of how rigorous your evaluation is, it is important to always reflect on your intervention before repeating in order to improve as an educator.

Discussion Models

One of the key aspects of bibliotherapy is discussion; this can take a myriad of forms, from Think, Pair, Share groups to the Grecian Paideia. Below are instructions for creating a discussion plan to use as the starting point for the conversation as well as a list of discussion models to try in your classroom.

When following this methodology, the most important aspect is what kinds of questions get asked.

When creating a discussion plan it is important to choose which aspects of the story to highlight and focus on. In our examples, we have chosen to highlight race, class, gender, orientation, and ability all as possible vectors by which to conduct discussion.

Focus on questions that challenge students to acknowledge their point of view and to recognize others. At the end of the day, only you know your students. Challenge them, but use your discression when choosing and writing questions.

These are the some scaled down questions that are frequently used in developmental bibliotherapy. These questions can be rewritten to suite the reading level of your students:

Are you like any of the story’s characters?
Do any of the characters remind you of someone?
Who would you like to be in the story?
Is there anything you would like to change about the story?
How would you change the characters, what happened, or how the story ended?
What is your favorite part of the story?
Did anything in the story ever happen to you?
What do you think will happen to the characters in this story tomorrow, in a few weeks, or a year from now?

Examples:

The Comet

Reading Activities

Post-Reading Strategies